My motive for doing what I am going to
do is simply personal
revenge. I do not expect to accomplish
anything by
it. Lincoln, Montana,
1996. This cabin is the chosen home of
Theodore J. Kazinski, more commonly
known as the Uni Bomber.
He's long been feared as America's
smartest criminal, a serial bomber who's
killed and wounded targets across the
country with no clear connection. For 17
years, he's eluded the FBI. It's the
largest, most expensive manhunt in the
bureau's history. He's the evil genius
they simply can't catch. Likely
history's most intellectual serial
killer. He's terrorized the nation,
instilling fear in Americans about
opening their mail and getting on
planes.
And he did it all from his
cabin. Here is where he built his bombs,
where he wrote his manifesto, and where
he evaded capture for nearly two
decades. It's where he turned from off
the grid recluse to world famous
murderer.
This cabin contains all the evidence the
FBI will need to convict
him. It's located deep in the Montana
wilderness. Back in 1969, Ted moved here
from California where he left behind a
shining career as a math professor at UC
Berkeley. He wanted to get closer to
nature and far far away from everyone
who pisses him off, which is most
people. He built this cabin with his
brother back when Ted still talked to
him, but it's got no electricity, no
plumbing, just a wood stove, a bed, and
a whole lot of
books. Right now, Ted is building
another bomb. They're meticulously
crafted, and he's continuously improving
his technique.
Every year they become more lethal. In
fact, he's got another one under his
bed, wrapped and ready to go. But he
won't get a chance to send it because
despite his intellect, he made some
pretty dumb mistakes.
[Music]
Time keeps
slipping. Set yourself for the
[Music]
trail. Goodbyes
ticket. Call it read that
t. You've got
me. You've got me.
You've got me.
This video is largely based on these two
books. Links are in the
description. We attribute the social and
psychological problems of modern society
to the fact that that society requires
people to live under conditions
radically different from those under
which the human race evolved.
Born in 1942, Ted grows up in a pretty
average family in the suburbs of
Chicago. They're workingclass Polish
Americans. His parents are politically
progressive, bookish, and intellectual,
and really into the outdoors. They're
strict, but loving. At least that's how
they remember it. It becomes obvious at
a young age that Ted is exceptionally
gifted, so his parents push him to
succeed. He skips two grades and easily
aces every class. He's a pretty normal
kid for someone with an IQ of 168. Sure,
Ted is quiet, shy around girls, and
arrogant, but he has a core circle of
friends, and plenty of hobbies. Like his
parents and brother, he loves playing
music, reading, and camping. People like
Ted. They'll later remember him as a
sensitive, respectful kid.
All that starts to change when Ted
enrolls at Harvard University at just 16
years old. Like many college freshmen,
Ted struggles to adjust. Here, he no
longer feels like the smartest person in
every room. And as a working-class kid
thrown into the world of America's
elite, he's a fish out of water. Other
students and even faculty mock his
shabby clothes and blue color
background. He's deeply bothered by
their snobbery, pain that will follow
him through life.
Ted's also just really young, younger
than almost everyone else on campus. As
an adult, Ted will write his mother
furious letters about this. He demands
apologies for pushing him out of the
house before he was ready. Ted becomes
depressed and his grades suffer. His
classmates describe him as a total
loner, moody, rude, and virtually mute.
He's that guy on the dorm floor who only
leaves his room to go to class, who
ignores everyone else. who slams doors.
There's a stench of rotting food wafting
from his room. Ted doesn't know it yet,
but his withdrawn and alienated demeanor
has caught the eye of a psychology
professor. Dr. Henry A. Murray is very
famous with an on-ampus research center
named after him. He's basically a god in
the social sciences. Murray is looking
out for particular types of students,
those who will make excellent guinea
pigs for an experiment. his final most
elaborate experiment, the capstone of a
long and illustrious career. It also
happens to be a CIA funded project
designed to cause extreme distress and
break down the subject's sense of
self. Clearly, we are in a position to
do a great deal of damage, and it does
appear that the FBI is not going to
catch us anytime soon. The FBI is a
joke.
[Music]
It's the 1970s in San Francisco. The
city is a hotbed of anti-government
activity. There's outrage over the
Vietnam War. Protest bombings are a
regular occurrence. Explosions happen
every week up through the mid80s. The
FBI dubs it the Belfast of North
America. Radical far-left groups like
the Weather Underground and the Symbion
Liberation Army claim credit for many of
the bombings. So most of the cases are
pretty straightforward in terms of
understanding motive and perpetrator.
But amidst all of this, the FBI San
Francisco bomb squad makes a shocking
discovery. 12 mysterious, similarly
built bombs can be linked to one elusive
killer or group. They have next to
nothing to go on. Just for whatever
unknown reason, this string of
explosives seems to target universities
and airlines. Whoever is building these
bombs is an expert crafter and careful
to not leave any DNA behind. Not a hair,
not a fiber. They're encased in
beautiful handmade wooden boxes. There
are no eyewitnesses to the bombings and
no letters from organizations claiming
credit. The victims appear to be
scattershot of random people. The
unknown perpetrator is referred to by
the code Unibomb for University and
airline bomber. So far, his bombs have
killed one person and injured 20 others
across five different
states. Unlucky recipients of the Uni
Bombers's early packages include a
campus security guard, a handful of
graduate students and professors, a
secretary, an airline executive, and
passengers on a flight from Chicago to
DC. Some are injured quite
badly. The first death is in 1985. Hugh
Scrutin, a guy who owned a computer
store in Sacramento and was about to get
married. What does he have to do with
anything at
[Music]
all? Far away in his cabin, Ted reads
about his death and chuckles to himself.
He hears that the FBI offers a $25,000
award for any information. He's
flattered. The uni bomber is making
waves. Not bad for the actions of one
man in a 10x 12 ft shack with no
electricity, running water, or phone
service. Pretty hard to imagine now.
These days, connection isn't optional.
It's how we get around, check in, look
stuff up, call for help, all of it.
That's where SY comes in. With
affordable global data in over 200
destinations in eight regions, SY is the
eSIM provider that keeps you online
while abroad. Forget hunting down local
SIM cards or getting slammed by roaming
charges. With SY, you'll be covered
before you even leave home. Just
download the app, pick your destination,
and activate your plan. Once you arrive
at your destination, your SY data plan
will activate automatically and you'll
never get stranded without service
again. SY gives you a heads up when your
data is running low. You can top up in
seconds. Simply download the SY app and
use code Fern TV to get an exclusive 15%
discount on your first purchase. Money
back guarantee in case your device is
not compatible. Back to Ted here in his
cabin. He's got everything he needs.
snowshoes, maps, a homemade chair, a
cot, a typewriter, and hundreds of
books. Scraps from junkyards and jars of
chemicals for making his bombs. Binders
and binders full of notes. All kinds of
disguises for delivering the bombs, like
wigs and sunglasses, and shoes with fake
souls. It's cramped to the gills, but
meticulously organized.
At this point, the FBI has zero
promising leads, and by the end of it
all, they'll never actually find the
perpetrator themselves. The bomber is
always several steps ahead of them.
They'll pursue thousands of dead ends,
spend hundreds of thousands of taxpayer
dollars, and pour countless man-hour
into this case. They have no idea why
he's targeting the people that he is.
But the bombs are so precise, so
wellcrafted. There's got to be a motive,
right? In 1987, there's finally a break
in the case. The uni bomber plants a
package outside a Salt Lake City
computer store, and a lady spots him.
He's wearing a gray hoodie, sunglasses,
and sporting a mustache. The police
create a sketch and post it all around
the country. The bombings immediately
stop, and for 5 years, nobody hears
anything from the uni bomber. All kinds
of people call him with tips, but the
leads go nowhere. The case pretty much
goes cold, but the FBI know that it's
only a matter of time before he'll
strike again. They're sure he's using
the time to perfect his bombs. And
they're right. In his cabin, Ted is
finessing his technique. The upcoming
bombs will be a whole lot more lethal.
But as the world will soon find out, he
is also busy writing. He doesn't just
want his explosives to do the talking.
He's crafting a manifesto, one that
claims to explain what the mysterious
string of bombings is all about.
The technopiles are taking us all on an
utterly reckless ride into the
unknown. Back at Harvard in 1958, the
United States is experiencing huge
shifts in culture. The button-up 50s are
drawing to a close and the nation
becomes swept up in the space race, the
civil rights movement, the sexual
revolution, the environmental movement,
the explosion of drug culture, and all
the while the Cold War is escalating.
The American military is paranoid that
communists have developed mind control
drugs and brainwashing techniques, and
they're eager to catch up. So, they're
covertly experimenting with ways to
manipulate
behavior. US intelligence officials are
especially interested in developing a
perfect truth drug for interrogating
enemies. and they believe LSD might be
it. But they're also testing a wide
range of ways that psychological
manipulation could bend the will of
anyone to do whatever the US military
wants. They've even enlisted help from
the Nazi scientists who experimented on
docow inmates with hallucinagens and
interrogation methods. The military
illegally smuggles these war criminals
over to get their advice on brainwashing
as part of Operation Paperclip.
Over the course of at least 11 years,
thousands of Americans are subjected to
unethical psychological experiments that
include sensory deprivation,
hallucinogenic drugs dose without
consent, subliminal messaging, hypnosis,
electroshock therapy, and even icepic
lobotoies. And that's just the stuff we
know about. When the project becomes
public knowledge in the 1970s, the CIA
director orders most of the records to
be destroyed. The program is codenamed
MK Ultra. Many of the test subjects are
vulnerable populations like prisoners
and hospital inmates, but also
students. Students are prime subjects
for these experiments because of their
frequent contact with professors who
play a big part in MK
Ultra. Some of the professors know the
role they play. Many don't. During the
postwar period, the CIA becomes the
largest employer of college professors,
and the military is by far the biggest
source of funding for psychological
research. Professors acted as
consultants and researchers for
militarybacked projects. They used their
status to encourage their students to
participate in experiments, often
involving drugs like
LSD. Afterwards, they reported back to
the government. Harvard becomes heavily
involved in army sponsored studies. One
of the CIA's main men on campus is the
superstar psych professor Henry Murray.
Murray is well known for his studies of
personality, and since the CIA's
beginnings, his theories have influenced
how they recruit new agents and how they
interrogate suspects. When Murray and
young Ted Kazinski cross paths, Murray
is at the end of his career, and he
recruits Ted for his final most
elaborate experiments. They're meant to
assess the effects of stress and harsh
interrogation on gifted male students.
Murray wants to know, "What will it take
to break an educated, intelligent man?"
The setup is simple. Ted and 21 other
students are asked to write an essay
about their most deep-seated beliefs.
Then they're told they'll discuss their
beliefs with a fellow undergrad. The
experiment aims to compare the effects
of stress on college men who seem
psychologically healthy and well
adjusted with students who seem
alienated, pessimistic, and lacking in
identity. Ted is most likely recruited
for the second group because he's
showing signs of
depression. Ted's personal essay stands
out as the most pessimistic of them all.
It suggests that he was already
vulnerable before the abusive test
began. He is also the youngest and the
poorest in the group. The students are
told this exercise is just to study
different personalities. In truth, now
the real experiment
begins. The essays are handed to lawyers
trained in manipulation who are
instructed to attack the values
expressed in them. The students endure
harsh interrogations in brightly lit
rooms. They face calculated personal
critiques designed to humiliate and
erode their sense of self. All the while
electrodes monitor their stress
responses. Later, they have to watch
these stressful and humiliating moments
on video over and over again for 3
years. As Mura himself describes it, the
tests were designed to be abusive. He's
had a lifelong fascination with pain and
stress and is known to have a sadistic
streak. Plenty of participants will
later report the experience to be deeply
unpleasant with lasting trauma. But
Ted's responses are the most extreme in
every category. Murray's team identifies
him as the most traumatized of
[Music]
all. Yes, Ted Kazinski got MK Ultra. You
can read all about it at
cia.gov. And consequence, many claim the
CIA created the uniomber, but that's an
oversimplification. It's not so easy to
prove how much effect the experiments
had on Ted's turn to terrorism. None of
the other students in the experiment are
known to have become killers. Some
psychologists believe the experiments
were stressful enough to create anger
problems in TED or even aggravate latent
schizophrenia. But other psychologists
evaluate him as undeniably sane. Ted
himself dismissed the idea that the
tests were anything resembling
psychological torture. He was very
invested in being seen as
psychologically healthy until the bitter
end. He's taking great pains to not be
painted as damaged or crazy. He wanted
his murders to be understood in the
context of his beliefs, not his personal
history. If people saw his actions as a
result of trauma or madness, it would
invalidate his ideas. Ideas that formed
his last year at
Harvard. Ted becomes increasingly
disillusioned with the industrial
technological system. He comes to
believe that technology is slowly
destroying humanity and eroding our
freedom. He's horrified by widespread
psychological suffering and how
industrial technology has severely
damaged the planet. He's certain that it
will only get worse the more technology
develops. So, anyone who helps advance
technology in any way is the enemy.
Scientists, engineers, business people,
what Ted calls the technician class. Ted
starts having revenge fantasies and
becomes obsessed with how society
enforces obedience with psychological
controls. He daydreams about breaking
away from society and living off the
grid. Ted graduates Harvard and goes on
to get his PhD in math at the University
of Michigan. He's quickly establishing
himself as a brilliant mathematician and
is offered a tenure track position at UC
Berkeley as their youngest professor
ever. His students don't like him very
much, but he's publishing groundbreaking
papers on boundary functions. But Ted
resigns one day without warning. He
tells his family that he's done with
teaching math to future engineers.
Engineers who will advance the
industrial technological system and
continue destroying the planet. Ted buys
a bit of land near Lincoln, Montana, and
builds a cabin with his brother. He's
ready to escape the advanced technology
that surrounded him at UC Berkeley. He
wants to live a simpler life, far away
from everyone he's ever known. And then
he starts to build his first
bomb. Through our bombings, we hope to
promote social instability, an
industrial society, propagate
anti-industrial ideas, and give
encouragement to those who hate the
industrial
system. In 1993, the uni bomber strikes
twice after a 6-year hiatus. Two
prominent researchers, a computer
scientist and a geneticist, receive
packages the size of a VHS tape. The
bombs detonate upon
opening and both professors are badly
injured. Shortly after, the New York
Times receives a typewritten letter. It
claims credit for the bombs and says the
public should expect more to come. In
1994 and 1995, the uni bomber succeeds
in killing two people with his mail
bombs, an advertising executive and a
forestry lobbyist. As feared, his
explosives have become notably more
sophisticated. Bombings are usually
accompanied with demands. Demands for
money or some kind of action. What made
the uni bomber so difficult to
understand and to find is that his bombs
never came with any requests. They seem
to be built only to cause fear, injury,
and
death. 17 years after starting his
bombing spree, the uni bomber finally
makes his demands known. He writes the
New York Times again announces that he
will permanently desist from terrorist
activities if they publish a 56-page
manifesto. The request kicks off a
fierce debate within the FBI and the
newspaper, to publish or not to publish.
The FBI has a clear policy to not
negotiate with terrorists, but they also
believe he'll honor his promise and stop
killing people. After all, this is what
the bombs were seemingly for, to force
people to pay attention to his views.
Plus, they still lack leads. If the
public reads the manifesto, someone
might be able to identify the uni
bomber. So, the manifesto is published.
The FBI decides it should just be the
Washington Post, though, because it has
fewer readers and the newspaper stands
will be easier to surveil, so they
think. Interest in the Uni Bomber is
huge. Newspaper sales hit a record high
that day with lines snaking around the
block. Across the country, Americans are
eager to finally read what the Uni
Bomber has to say. The manifesto opens
with an iconic line. The industrial
revolution and its consequences have
been a disaster for the human race. And
though the manifesto is an argument that
calls for dismantling industrial
society, it's also unwittingly a
self-portrait. Within its pages, the Uni
Bomber has accidentally unmasked
himself. David and Ted, though 7 years
apart and very different, grew up close
and loved each other very much. As
adults, they had impassion philosophical
debates by male and shared a lot of the
same views. David also worried about
technologies destructive effect on
humanity. He'd also spent some time
living off the grid in a self-made
cabin. But David wasn't a killer. When
the manifesto is published, he hasn't
spoken to his brother in a long time.
Ted cut him out when David got married
and refused to answer any of his
letters. David's wife, Linda, a
philosophy professor, has a funny
feeling about Ted, whom she never met.
As the bombings stack up and some of the
timings coincide with Ted's travels,
Linda tells David, "You've got a screwy
brother. Maybe he's the uni bomber."
David doesn't want to hear it. Linda
doesn't know Ted the way David does.
He'd never kill anybody. As a kid, Ted
used to cry at the thought of animals
getting hurt. But when the manifesto is
finally published, David avoids reading
it. He doesn't want to admit the
similarities, that like the Uni Bomber,
Ted is an excellent carpenter, and that
he had a lifelong fascination with
explosives, and that some of the dates
match up perfectly with Ted's travels.
David only reads it when Linda insists.
His jaw literally drops from the first
few lines. The killer, like Ted, also
hates technology. As he continues, David
recognizes idiosyncratic word choices
and logical arguments that Ted uses all
the time. There is no escaping the
truth. Ted is the
uniomber. So, after some moral qualms
about betraying his brother, David
alerts the FBI.
They are bound to make me out to be a
sicky and to ascribe to me motives of
assorted or sick type. Many tamed
conformist types seem to have a powerful
need to depict the enemy of society as
sorted, repulsive, or
[Music]
sick. Lincoln, Montana, April
1996. With a tip from David, the feds
are staking out Ted's cabin. The
investigation is meant to be conducted
quietly, but they're interviewing local
towns people, trying to collect more
evidence on Ted. Right now, all they
have is the linguistic similarities in
the manifesto and old letters from Ted
that David gave the FBI. Not exactly
cold, hard proof, enough for a search
warrant, but not an arrest. Rumors start
to spread around town that Ted Kazinski,
their very own angry hermit, is the uni
bomber. The plan is to draw Ted out of
his cabin and get inside before he can
escape or destroy any evidence. But they
don't know if he has it tricked out with
explosives. Nobody would be surprised if
he
did. Ted has no idea he's under
surveillance. So when someone knocks and
says some land surveyors need to talk,
he believes them and opens the
door. He wasn't expecting visitors.
These days, he's busy with a dirty job.
He's in the middle of rasping aluminum
blocks to make powder for more bombs.
He's covered from head to toe in the
dust. He's rail thin because the rabbit
hunting was scarce this season. Ted's
hair is wild and his clothes are
literally rotting off of his body. But
what does he care? He's not trying to
impress anyone, and he can clean up fast
if he needs to blend into society. Too
bad for Ted. He'll be photographed in
the state, filthy, emaciated, and in
severe need of a shave. The image will
circulate around the globe and will not
help Ted's desire to seem
sane. When the feds swoop in, they find
40,000 pages of journals and plans, most
written in code. The code is more
complex than anything the FBI had ever
seen, more convoluted than codes the KGB
used during the Cold War. But Ted also
left the key to the code in the cabin.
Without it, the FBI wouldn't be able to
decipher the decades of written
confessions that definitively tied Ted
to the bombings. They also find a bomb
under the bed ready to be mailed to an
aerospace company in Dallas. Now the FBI
has all the evidence they need. They
lock up the cabin and take Ted to
prison. He does not dispute that the
journals with the confessions are his.
In fact, he wrote them partially so that
nobody would try to say he was crazy.
Ted's family and his defense team
attempt to convince the jury and the
world at large that he is mentally ill.
They're doing anything they can to avoid
the death penalty, which frustrates him.
He tries to fire his lawyers than defend
himself. He would rather die than allow
his lawyers to plead not guilty by
reason of insanity. Ted pleads guilty to
his crimes and is sentenced to life in
prison. Behind bars, he never stops
writing. He publishes two books and
keeps up a lively correspondence with a
wide array of journalists and admirers.
He also finally makes some human
connections. He strikes up a friendship
with Timothy McVey, the Oklahoma City
bomber who killed 168 people in 1995.
Ted and McVey are briefly on the same
prison block and find they have a lot of
views in common before McVey is carded
off to death row. Ted even finds love
for the first time in his life. After a
lifetime of struggling to connect with
women and never going beyond a few
kisses, Ted suddenly has dozens of women
writing him romantic or salacious
letters. But only one captures his
heart, a school teacher he calls his
lady love. They spend thousands of hours
talking by mail or in visiting booths,
but they are never able to touch. He
writes classical music for her before
she dies of lung cancer. Later, Ted also
develops cancer. When the condition
becomes advanced, he dies by suicide in
June 2023 at 81 years old.
[Music]
This is not to be a political
revolution. Its object will be to
overthrow not governments but the
economic and technological basis of the
present
society. In the decades since his
arrest, Ted Kazinski continues to
fascinate and sometimes inspire. The
manifesto's central argument is that
technological advancements since the
industrial revolution have robbed people
of their freedom and well-being. These
advancements are supposedly responsible
for widespread psychological suffering
and environmental devastation. It's a
revolutionary call to dismantle
industrial society altogether and warns
that technology will inevitably
overpower human
autonomy. Many of Kazinsk's observations
in the manifesto are true. Some of his
predictions are preient and a lot of the
grievances are understandable. It's not
hard to find people who are also
frustrated with surveillance or sad
about environmental destruction.
At the time of his capture, Time
magazine wrote, "There's a little bit of
the uni bomber in most of us." Nowadays,
Ted Kazinski continues to find admirers
online. From teens on Tik Tok depressed
about climate change, half ironically
saluting Uncle Ted, to the extreme right
mass murderer Anders Bavik, who heavily
quoted Kazinski's industrial society in
his own manifesto. But even if most
people can find parts in the manifesto
they agree with, most people are not
willing to kill. Kazinski knew that most
people would be repelled by his crimes
but committed them anyway. Those who
find the ideas compelling might want to
check out Jacquel, the thinker whose
ideas most inspired the manifesto. The
philosopher never advocated killing.
They also should check out Ted
Kazinski's diaries. They lay bare the
personal motivations that drove the uni
bomber beyond the manifesto that was
polished for public
consumption. Technological society
really did seem to anger Ted, but Ted
was also very, very angry in general.
In his diary, Ted Kazinski writes that
he was happy to kill innocent civilians.
He took pleasure in causing people pain.
He killed at least nine dogs just
because they barked too loud. He hated
leftists. He hated doctors. He hated
women. He fantasized about killing them
just for rejecting him. He fantasized
about killing his neighbors just because
they annoyed him, including a toddler.
He condemned technology as slavery and
glorified simpler times that ran on,
actual slavery. Kazinski wasn't even
much of an environmentalist. He made fun
of them in his diaries. He littered
proudly. He poached illegally. He logged
on protected lands. You might get the
sense that he only used environmentalism
as a post hawk justification for his
murders. a cynic who identified
ecological concerns as the most
acceptable excuse for killing.
[Music]